Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף daf. *daf* is למד *lamed*,
מנחות *Menachos* 30, we are back on track with the דף daf
*daf* with the where we're up to, and we pick up in
the middle of דף למד *daf lamed*,
and אמר רב Rav, יהושע Yehoshua *Amar Rav Yehoshua*. The line starts
with the word רב Rav יהושע Yehoshua *Rav Yehoshua*, רב יהושע Yehoshua
*Rav Yehoshua* it is about 12 lines from the top, and we
were in the middle of talking about how a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah, *sefer Torah* has to be written. We had the, of course,
wonderful גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about when משה Moshe, *Moshe* went up to
receive the ספר תורה Sefer Torah, *sefer Torah*, and now we're going
to look about an interesting discussion, theological and halakhic, about the last
eight פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* in the תורה Torah. *Torah*. So let's take
a look. אמר רב יהושע בר אבא אמר רב גידל Rav Giddel
אמר רב שמונה פסוקים shmona pesukim שבתורה יחיד קורא אותן yachid kore
otan, בבית הכנסת *Amar Rav Yehoshua bar Abba Amar Rav Giddel Amar
Rav: Shmonah pesukim shebaTorah yachid korei otan beveit haknesset*. The eight פסוקים
pesukim *pesukim*, last eight פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* of the תורה Torah *Torah*,
an individual reads them in the בית כנסת *beit knesset*. So we
will unpack what the word יחיד קורא אותן yachid kore otan *yachid
korei otan* means in a minute, but let's first understand what's important
about these last eight פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says: כמאן *Ke-man*? Who is this going like? דלא כרבי שמעון *De-lo
ke-Rabbi Shimon*. It seems like it's not like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon*. דתניא *Detanya*: וימת שם משה Moshe עבד ה׳ *Vayamot sham
Moshe eved Hashem*, and משה Moshe *Moshe* the servant of God died
there in ערבות מואב *Arvot Moav*. This is at the very end
of
דברים *Devarim*. The eight last פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* start with משה Moshe
*Moshe* dying, and then כל ישראל *kol Yisrael* mourned him and לא
קם נביא עוד בישראל *lo kam navi od beYisrael* and so on.
אפשר משה Moshe חי וכתב וימת שם משה Moshe *Efshar Moshe chai
vekhatav vayamot sham Moshe*? So is it possible, the ברייתא Baraisa, *Baraita*
says, that משה Moshe *Moshe* was alive and he wrote "And משה
Moshe *Moshe* died there"? I mean, that would have been patently false.
I mean, it would have been very profoundly sad for משה Moshe,
*Moshe*, but also patently false that he was writing it while he
was still alive. אלא עד כאן כתב ktav משה Moshe, מכאן ואילך
כתב יהושע בן ben נון *Ella ad kan katav Moshe, mikan ve'eilakh
katav Yehoshua bin Nun*. דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rabbi Yehuda. *Divrei Rabbi
Yehuda*. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* says rather, the last
eight פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* were not written by משה Moshe, *Moshe*, they
were written by יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua bin Nun*. Something that if
somebody were to say today, we would think would be the height
of כפירה *kefira*, and here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is
saying actually those eight פסוקים psukim. *pesukim* were scribed by יהושע *Yehoshua*.
ואמרי לה רבי נחמיה *Ve-amrei lei Rabbi
Nechemia*, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and some say
רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia* says. אמר לו רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Amar
lo Rabbi Shimon*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* said back to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* slash רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia*: אפשר
ספר תורה Sefer Torah חסר אות אחת *Efshar sefer Torah chaser oti
echat*? Is it possible the ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah* should
be missing even one letter? וכתיב *U-ketiv*: לקוח את ספר sefer התורה
הזה ושמתם אותו *Lakoach et sefer hatorah hazeh vesamtem oto*, take this
ספר תורה Sefer Torah. *sefer Torah* and place it near the ארון
*Aron*. That was what משה Moshe *Moshe* said to the בני לוי
*Bnei Levi*, and if he's calling it a ספר תורה Sefer Torah,
*sefer Torah*, he obviously means the complete ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer
Torah*. So clearly משה Moshe *Moshe* had written the complete ספר תורה
Sefer Torah, *sefer Torah* when he gave it to the לויים *Levi'im*.
So clearly he wrote those last eight פסוקים psukim, *pesukim* as well.
Now, that line אפשר ספר תורה Sefer Torah חסר אות אחת *Efshar
sefer Torah chaser oti echat* could be just read as, you know,
a practical statement of when משה Moshe, *Moshe* says "take this ספר
תורה Sefer Torah, *sefer Torah*", ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah* means
a complete ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*. But it sounds also
like it's more deeply theological. Is it possible that the תורה *Torah*
that we received from משה Moshe *Moshe* was not fully, you know,
written or given from God to משה *Moshe*? Like, aren't we supposed
to believe that the entire תורה *Torah* was from directly from משה
*Moshe*? I mean, from God through משה *Moshe*. So how is that
possible? So it must be that משה *Moshe* actually did write the
last eight פסוקים psukim. *pesukim*. How about the problem that like how
could משה *Moshe* write it when it was false at the time
of writing? אלא עד
כאן הקדוש ברוך הוא אומר ומשה כותב kotev. ואומר *Ella ad kan
Hakadosh Barukh Hu omer uMoshe kotev ve'omer*, some of the גרסא *girsa*
אומר וכותב vekhotev. *omer vekotev*. So up until these last eight פסוקים
psukim. *pesukim*, God would say to משה *Moshe* what to write and
משה *Moshe* would say it out loud and then write it himself.
Right, and that's what they do when scribes write a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah, *sefer Torah* or מזוזות *mezuzot* or תפילין *tefillin*, in order
to make sure they're not making a mistake, they say out loud
the word and then they write. Okay, so that's what משה *Moshe*
would do, he would repeat back to God and write. מכאן ואילך
*Mikan ve'eilakh*, and when it came back to these last eight פסוקים
psukim *pesukim*, הקדוש ברוך הוא אומר ומשה כותב בדמע kotev bedema *Hakadosh
Barukh Hu omer uMoshe kotev bedema*. And משה *Moshe* wrote it with
crying. So what does this mean "with crying"? So רש״י Rashi, *Rashi*
says what it means is, rather than saying it back, it was
so painful to say "and משה *Moshe* died". I mean, how should
משה *Moshe* be saying those words? So when he wrote the last
eight פסוקים *pesukim*, he didn't say them out loud. It was still
from God to משה *Moshe*, משה *Moshe* wrote everything, but rather than
saying it out loud, instead he was crying as he was writing
those last eight words. A very poignant picture. כמה שנאמר להלן *Kemashenemar
lehalan*, as it says over there by ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu*: ויאמר להם ברוך
מפיו יקרא אלי את כל הדברים האלה ואני כותב על הספר בדיו
*Vayomer lahem Barukh, mi-piv yikra elai et kol hadevarim ha'eleh va'ani kotev
al hasefer bidyo*. From his mouth, you know, ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* would read
this to me, ברוך *Barukh* was ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu*'s scribe. סופר sofer and
I would write on the book with ink. Okay, so what does
that prove? So רש"י Rashi says, well it proves he says I
would write, but it didn't say I would say back and write,
and that is also because that this was about, you know, איכה,
Eicha, this was about tragedy, and therefore like משה, he would not
say the words back, he was actually crying when he said it,
or certainly wasn't verbalizing them back, although it does not say that.
Okay, so according to רש"י, Rashi, or you know, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is just explaining like the poignancy of the difficulty of משה
writing this, but he doesn't really deal with the question of how
could משה be writing something that is false? So at the time,
at least at the time of the writing. So the מהרש"א, Maharsha,
not here but in בבא בתרא Bava Batra where this also appears,
has a brilliant read of this. And he says that רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon. is saying two things different from רבי יהודה. Number one,
he is saying that, you know, where it says משה אומר וכותב,
Moshe omer vekhotev, you know, משה used to write and say, or
actually I should say two things different from the way it was
until that point and the last eight פסוקים. Until that point, it
was משה אומר וכותב, Moshe omer vekhotev, and from this point on
it's just משה כותב. Moshe kotev. He just wrote it and he
didn't say it back, and that was already one type of a
שינוי, shinui, if you would, one type of a thing that signaled
that it was different, which signaled that, yes, these were written even
though they weren't true at yet at the time of writing. It
was being signaled by the fact that he was not saying it
out loud. Okay, so not just because of the poignancy and it
was difficult, but it was a way to signal that the last
eight פסוקים were different in the sense that they had not yet
happened. Okay, then he also says that the word, so that's כותב
אומר וכותב kotev omer vekhotev versus just כותב. And then he says
very brilliantly that כותב בדמע is in contrast to כותב בדיו. kotev
bidyo. Okay, and he would write with tears, it was like invisible
ink, that משה actually wrote, he didn't write with ink, the last
eight פסוקים were written with משה'ס Moshe's tears. And it was like,
and therefore it's like beautifully maintains that tension, or you know, that
sort of dealing with the theological issue that משה had to have
written the whole ספר תורה, sefer Torah, and the fact that he
wrote it before it was true yet. So he sort of wrote
it in invisible ink. He wrote the whole ספר תורה, sefer Torah
but the last eight פסוקים were in tears, and maybe יהושע went
afterwards and he filled it out with ink, and therefore you have
him addressing the problem that רבי יהודה raised. I believe the וילנא
גאון Vilna Gaon says something similar. He says that it was sort
of like the tear means like a drop of ink that had
not yet transformed into the exact letters. And you know, and then
יהושע took that drop of ink and turned them into the appropriate
letters. But some way of holding both the idea that it all
came from משה and that at some level משה couldn't have physically,
have actually written those words, at least not in the normal way,
while they had not yet happened. Okay, so that is a fascinating
theological debate around that. And the גמרא Gemara says, so it seems
that if you're going to give the last eight פסוקים a different
status, that say יחיד קורא אותן, yachid kore otan. that only an
individual reads them, we'll get back to again what that phrase means,
it seems that that is not like רבי שמעון. It seems like
that's רבי יהודה who says that they were written by יהושע and
therefore they have a different status. So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו
תימא רבי שמעון, afillu teima Rabbi Shimon, no, even this special idea
of יחיד קורא אותן yachid kore otan could go like רבי שמעון
who says they were written by משה, הואיל ואישתני אישתני, ho'il ve'ishtani
ishtani, why, since they were changed, they are different, right, he didn't
repeat them back, he was crying, he wrote them in tears, so
even though they were written by משה, they are different than what
came before, and that gives it this special status of יחיד קורא
אותן. yachid kore otan So what does יחיד קורא yachid korei, אותן
mean? So רש"י Rashi says יחיד קורא אותן means that you have
only one individual can get all eight פסוקים. You cannot break up
those שמונה פסוקים to two, you know, two עליות. aliyot. All right,
because it's different, because it's different, we have to treat it as
a single unit, different, okay, and that reflects its different status. Okay,
that's what רש"י Rashi says. It's apparently also the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תוספות
Tosafot suggests an answer by רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, or suggests an
answer, excuse me,
that it means that the בעל קורא ba'al kore would not read
alongside the עולה. ole. The עולה ole would have to read it
by himself. Only an individual would read it, not with the assistance
like of a בעל קורא, ba'al kore, that he quotes in the
name of רב משולם. Rav Meshullam. The problem with that explanation as
תוספות Tosafot says is that in the time of the גמרא Gemara
there was no בעל קורא. ba'al kore. There was just the עולה.
ole. So it can't be that that is the contrast that the
גמרא Gemara, is
making. Although you can understand though that's very poignant as well, in
a sense almost that there's something a little more lonely rather than
assisted by those last eight פסוקים. Anyway, that's basically, תוספות Tosfos in
the end agrees with רש״י, Rashi it means only one עולה. oleh.
Now רמב״ם Rambam has a fascinating פסק psak here. And רמב״ם Rambam
says the following in הלכות תפילה פרק י״ג הלכה ו. Hilchos Tefilla
Perek Yud Gimmel Halacha Vav. He says שמונה פסוקים שבסוף התורה מותר
לקרות אותם בבית הכנסת בפחות מעשרה. Shmoneh psukim shebesof haTorah mutar likros
osam beveis haknesses befachos measarah.
When you get to those last eight פסוקים, you can read them
with less than a full מנין. minyan. Why not? He says אף
על פי שכל התורה יהיו משה מפי הגבורה אמרם. Af al pi
shekol haTorah heyu Moshe mipi haGevurah amram. Let's get it clear here,
we פסק pasken like רבי שמעון. Everything was straight from God to
משה, משה wrote everything including those last eight פסוקים. Okay, so הואיל
ומשמעם שהם אחר מיתת משה הרי נשתנו. Hoil umashmaam sheheim achar misas
Moshe harei nishtanu.
So רמב״ם Rambam says what was different about them was not the
way they were written, that משה was crying, it was written with
tears, whatever the איבעיא ibaya of the גמרא Gemara, is. They're different
in that, yes, they were written by משה, but the sense is
they sound like they happened after משה died. So because of that,
because of that like little
jarring dissonance there, that is why they have a somewhat different status,
ולפיכך מותר ליחיד לקרות אותן. ulefichach mutar leyachid likros osan. Therefore it
could be read without a ציבור. tzibur. Okay, now that's a little
funny because that seems to be communicating a lesser status if we
allow it to be done without a ציבור. tzibur. So until now
we have not been suggesting a lesser status, just you have to
recognize that they're unique and they're different. That's what רמב״ם Rambam says.
ראב״ד Raavad does not like this at all. ראב״ד Raavad says like
this: לא שמענו דבר זה מעולם. Lo shamanu davar zeh meolam. We've
never heard of such a thing. ומה שאמרו יחיד קורא אותם לומר
שאינו מפסיק בהם. Umah sheamru yachid korei osam lomar sheeino mafsik bahem.
Okay, he says what it means יחיד קורא, it's just like רש״י
said, you don't interrupt it, one person עולה oleh gets all eight
together.
And then he says מקומות הללו נהגו שהעולה לקרות בתורה הוא לבדו
קורא ואין החזן קורא עמו. Mekomos halalu nahagu shehaoleh likros baTorah hu
levado korei veein hachazzan korei imo. And then he says exactly what
תוספות Tosfos says, not as explanation in the גמרא, Gemara. תוספות Tosfos
is right this can't be the explanation of the גמרא, Gemara but
he says the practice is also that it's only the עולה oleh
reads it and a בעל קורא baal korei does not assist him.
Again, there's something there I think a little forlorn or lonely or
you're on this by yourself that maybe evokes that sense of what
was happening during those last eight פסוקים. And then he's got one
final great line responding to רמב״ם Rambam and he says ומה
שכתב הוא עניין זרות הוא. Umah shekasav hu inyan zarus hu. What
רמב״ם Rambam said is particularly bizarre or strange, מאוד, meod, וציבור היכן
הלכו, vetzibur heichan halchu, where did the ציבור tzibur go? What do
you mean you can read them without a ציבור? tzibur? What were
you reading right before that? I mean it's שמחת תורה Simchas Torah
here or whatever it is, you had a מנין minyan for the
first six עליות aliyos and then what, all of a sudden you're
left with only nine? I mean I guess it could happen, you
have a small מנין, minyan, one of them leaves, but it's a
little bit bizarre that we would be פסקנינג paskening for that, a
special status for that particular case. Okay, so that is the interesting
story about the last eight פסוקים of the תורה. Going back to
the גמרא. Gemara רמי בר אבא אמר רב גידל אמר רב. Rami
bar Abba amar Rav Giddel amar Rav. Said רמי בר אבא Rami
bar Abba in the name of רב גידל in the name of
רב, הלוקח ספר תורה מן השוק, Halokeiach Sefer Torah min hashuk, if
somebody purchases a ספר תורה sefer Torah from the marketplace, כחוטף מצווה
מן השוק, Kechoitef mitzvah min hashuk, you're just grabbing a מצווה. mitzvah.
It's like you're not putting in any effort, you're going into the
supermarket, you're buying it, okay, you wrote a check, very nice, it
was not really producing something in a serious way, real effort in
terms of producing the מצווה. mitzvah. Not just effort, we'll talk, it
also didn't contribute, you didn't add a ספר sefer, תורה to the
world, right, by you didn't write it, you just, it just transferred
ownership. You took it away from someone and maybe that's also the
idea of חוטף, choitef, somebody else lost it, you got it. Okay,
so okay, you got a מצווה mitzvah because now you own a
ספר sefer תורה. Assume that's a מצווה, mitzvah, it's more of a
מצווה mitzvah to write a ספר תורה, maybe owning it is somewhat
like writing it. But nowadays people commission it or they'll get a
ספר תורה that was rescued from the Holocaust and they'll hire somebody
to fix it. Okay, but just purchasing it you're just switching hands,
you got a מצווה mitzvah but it was sort of like you
stole a מצווה mitzvah almost.
כתבו, Kasvo, if you actually wrote a ספר תורה, מעלה עליו הכתוב
כאילו קיבלו מהר סיני, Maalah alav hakasuv keilu kiblo mehar Sinai, then
it's treated as if you received it from הר סיני. Har Sinai.
And that really speaks to when you write it down, just the
act of writing and this is even more I think than just
commissioning it. Commissioning it, you get a new ספר תורה produced at
least and you're invested in a deeper way than if you're just
writing a check and purchasing one that exists, but writing it... You
really much more deeply connect to the words themselves. There's a much
greater sense of ownership, and that's what כאילו קיבלה מהר סיני Ke'ilu
kibeilah me-Har Sinai is. It's like you ממש mamash received it from
הר סיני. Har Sinai. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, אם הגיה
אפילו אות אחת, im hegiah afilu ot achat, if you corrected even
one letter, if even one letter was off and you fixed it,
מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו כתבו, ma'aleh alav hakatuv ke'ilu ketavo, the Torah
treats it as as if you wrote it. Now, you don't get
to go up all the steps of the ladder. It's as if
you wrote it, but it's not as if you received it at
הר סיני. Har Sinai. If you actually write it, then it's like
you received it at הר סיני, Har Sinai, then you connect it
to the entire thing. If you fixed it, it's like you wrote
it. It's, you know, you actually made it from, some of the
מפרשים mefarshim say, not usable to usable, you actually did a degree
of writing, you were involved at least in one letter. You know,
people sometimes when they participate in the writing of a ספר תורה,
they'll buy a letter, they'll have a little way of assisting the
סופר to write a letter, and it gives them a personal connection.
So even though, so it's a personal connection like we'll give you
a one-degree upgrade as if you wrote the whole thing. But if
you actually write the whole thing, then it's as if you received
it at הר סיני. Har Sinai. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanna rabanan, our
rabbis taught: עושה אדם יריעה מבת שלוש דפים, oseh adam yeriah mi-bat
shalosh dapim, שלוש דפים, shalosh dapim,
you can make one קלף, klaf, you know, they would, ספר תורה
is made by sewing together different parchments. So in any one parchment,
it can have three, minimum three columns, ועד בת שמונה דפים, v'ad
bat shemoneh dapim, and a maximum of eight columns. You don't want
it to be too narrow, you don't want it to be too
wide, you know, it's sort of good for the קלף klaf and
for the ספר that there be a reasonable amount of spacing between
the תפירות, tfirot, you know, between the the points where they're sewn
to the next קלף, klaf, a reasonable amount of spacing, but not,
you know, but not too much.
Okay. פחות מכאן ויתר מכאן לא יעשה, pachot mikan v'yeter mikan lo
ya'aseh, more than this or less than this you shouldn't do. Now
with all these things about instructions, a lot of them sound like
it's not הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, it's like advice, it's
aesthetics, and more than advice, it's
לכתחילה. le-chatchila. Does not sound like it would invalidate. Okay. ולא ירבה
בדפים, v'lo yarbeh ba-dapim, and we'll see more about this coming up.
ולא ירבה בדפים, v'lo yarbeh ba-dapim, and you should not have, you
know, do more than have a lot of, what do you call
it,
columns if that's not the natural fit for the קלף. klaf. וזהו
רש"י, v'zehu Rashi, this is how Rashi reads it, מפני שנראה איגרת,
mipnei she-nirah iggeret, because it will look like a letter, meaning, not
yes, you're not going to have more than eight, but if the
normal size, if it's a small קלף, klaf, you should only have
three or four columns. Don't try to get six, seven, or eight
columns into a small קלף klaf even though you're allowed up to
eight, because then you'll have very narrow columns, and then that'll be
like, you know, it'll seem more like a letter. I guess they
would write letters in narrow columns.
Okay. ולא ימעיט בדפים, v'lo yama'it ba-dapim, and don't have, you know,
fewer columns than is appropriate for the קלף, klaf, meaning very wide
columns, מפני שעיניו משוטטות, mipnei she-einav meshottetot, because your eyes wander, meaning
if it's a very wide column, you know, you're reading to the
long end of a very, very long line, and then you have
to go back to the beginning of of the next line and
you'll lose your place. Okay. So you want the columns to be
of reasonable width, not too short, not too narrow, not too wide.
Interesting line here about, okay, well the speed: אלא כגון למשפחותיהם למשפחותיכם
למשפחותיכם ג' פעמים. ela kigon le-mishpachoteihem le-mishpachoteichem le-mishpachoteichem gimmel pa'amim. Okay. The
appropriate sort of width of a column should be to fit in
three times למשפחותיכם, le-mishpachoteichem, three ten-letter words would be like the appropriate
width. Now, now,
what do you call it? Now,
תוספות Tosafot says in the name of רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam that
that's only if the כתב is very narrow. But if you're writing
like with big thick nice ספר תורה letters, as we're used to
seeing in a ספר תורה, you know, then your eyes won't wander
as much and it could be longer than just than just thirty
letters. Okay. נזדמנה לו יריעה בת תשעה דפים, nizdamna lo yeriah bat
tisha dapim, now let's say you happen to get a piece of
קלף klaf that could fit nine columns. So you don't want to
do that, so you're going to cut it in half. So לא
יחלוק שלוש לכאן ושש לכאן, lo yachlok shalosh lekan v'shesh lekan, don't
divide it into a three-column קלף klaf and a six-column קלף, klaf,
אלא ארבע לכאן וחמש לכאן, ela arba lekan v'chamesh lekan, four and
five, five and four, it looks nicer when the קלפים klafim are
roughly similar sizes. Okay. במה דברים אמורים בתחילת הספר, bameh devarim amurim
bit-chilat ha-sefer, when is this true that, you know, that you have
to that you shouldn't have too many or too few columns when
you are, you know, at the beginning of the ספר, meaning the
entire ספר until the very end. אבל בסוף הספר, aval be-sof ha-sefer,
but when you get to the end, אפילו פסוק אחד ואפילו דף
אחד, afilu pasuk echad v'afilu daf echad, even one פסוק pasuk and
one דף. and one column, meaning imagine that you, you know, you're
at your very last קלף klaf and you got to fig... and
you've got you have one פסוק pasuk left but you can't get
it to the end of the column. So you have to start
a new column and you have to start a new קלף. klaf.
So okay fine if you're at the very end you can go
ahead and even have just one פסוק pasuk to a column and
to a column. So the גמרא Gemara
says ובסוף הספר אפילו פסוק אחד ואפילו בדף אחד, u'v'sof hasefer afilu
pasuk echad v'afilu b'daf echad, even one פסוק pasuk in one column.
So the גמרא gemara says פסוק אחד סלקא דעתך? pasuk echad salka
dach? One פסוק pasuk in a column? How can you do that?
Now why not? That seems to be exactly what we're saying that
you can, we allow you. But the way some of the מפרשים
meforshim explain this is because we learned before that you're supposed to
end at the end of a column. So how can you say
you can start at the top of a column, get one פסוק
pasuk in for an entire קלף klaf if you have to end
at the end of a column? That's how some understand this question.
אלא אימא פסוק אחד בדף אחד. ela eima pasuk echad b'daf echad.
Fine. So how does that solve it? One פסוק pasuk in one
column. So what it means is one פסוק pasuk fills an entire
column, that if you were left with your final קלף klaf of
the ספר תורה, you had one פסוק pasuk left to go, so
okay on the one hand you're only going to have one column
in this קלף klaf and not three because you have no choice,
you only have one column left. How do you deal with the
fact that the פסוק pasuk has to be at the end, that
a column has to get to the bottom? So you write it
in very big letters, one word extremely narrow, one word to a
line until you get, so you can have one פסוק pasuk fill
out the entire column. Some ראשונים rishonim say you even had to
write in very big letters. All right.
שיעור גיליון, shiur gilyon, so that is how many columns to a
קלף. klaf. Now now we're going to talk about margins. Anybody who's
ever written anything in Microsoft Word and you get to tweak with
the margins, right margin, left margin, top, bottom, line spacing, that's what
we're going to do now. שיעור גיליון, shiur gilyon, the size of
the margin, מלמטה טפח, milmata tefach, the bottom margin is a
טפח. tefach. מלמעלה שלש אצבעות milmala shalosh etzbaos is three אצבעות, etzbaos,
a little smaller. טפח tefach is ארבע אצבעות. arba etzbaos. Why? Because
since you're most likely to like rest your hand or whatever at
the bottom, you want there to be or sometimes maybe I don't
know it gets also scrolled up at the bottom, you want there
to be a little extra space at the bottom.
ובין דף לדף כמלא רוחב שתי אצבעות u'vein daf l'daf kimlo rouchav
shtei etzbaos is the width of שתי אצבעות. shtei etzbaos. ובחומשים u'v'chumashim
now if you're dealing with a codex then the margins are slightly
less. מלמטה שלש אצבעות מלמעלה שתי אצבעות, milmata shalosh etzbaos milmala shtei
etzbaos, the bottom three, the top two. ובין דף לדף כמלא רוחב
גודל u'vein daf l'daf kimlo rouchav godel and between the columns one
width of a thumb. Clearly when it's talking about a codex these
are aesthetic like proper for כבוד, kavod, for reading, ease of reading,
not making mistakes. It is, but it's not like a הלכה halacha
of being כשר kosher or פסול pasul and one gets the same
sense in terms of the ספר תורה as well. Okay but again
that's not spelled out. ובין שיטה לשיטה כמלא שיטה. u'vein shita l'shita
kimlo shita. Now between each line is the width of a line,
so it's what we would call double spacing between the lines. ובין
תיבה לתיבה כמלא אות קטנה u'vein teiva l'teiva kimlo os ktana between
each one word and the next word you have to have the
space of a small letter like a letter יוד. yud. How do
you know that break up the words? All right. Sometimes a ספר
תורה is written and it all looks like one word, there's not
enough of a break. ובין אות לאות כמלא חוט השערה, u'vein os
l'os kimlo chut hasa'ara, what's the spacing between each
letter? That could even be a hairbreadth but they do have to
be separate. If they're not separate the letters they're not כשר. kosher.
אל ימעט אדם את הכתב לא מפני רווח של מטה ולא מפני
רווח של מעלה. al yimaet adam es hak'sav lo mipnei revach shel
mata v'lo mipnei revach shel ma'ala. Don't make the script smaller than
the rest of the script of the column in order to get
the right sized margins. Okay so you did the scoring, you know,
the making of the indent in the קלף klaf and you're coming
to write it and now you realize like oh the scoring it
was done a little close
to the top of the קלף klaf or to the bottom of
the קלף. klaf. It's going to get me, I'm not going to
have the right margin of a טפח tefach or of שלש אצבעות.
shalosh etzbaos. Even so, even though you won't have the right margin,
do not try to adjust the letter size different from what the
letter size is in the rest
of the תורה just in order to get the full margin space.
אל ימעט אדם את הכתב לא מפני רווח של מטה ולא מפני
רווח של מעלה. al yimaet adam es hak'sav lo mipnei revach shel
mata v'lo mipnei revach shel ma'ala. Now I have to tell you
I don't exactly understand the רווח של מעלה revach shel ma'ala because
as opposed to how we write where our lines go under the
letters, the way scoring works is scoring the scoring is on the
top of the letters. So you know you can understand at the
bottom you know if you don't want to make it you might
make it smaller so you have the full margin at the bottom.
But at the top if you're operating within the scoring making it
smaller is not going to increase your margin. The margin is from
the top of letters. I don't know maybe they're talking about like
the למדס lameds or the things that go above the scoring. Okay
anyway ולא מפני רווח שבין שיטה לשיטה velo mipnei revach shebein shita
leshita also don't make your letters smaller than the norm in order
to get you know the full double spacing between the two lines.
ולא מפני רווח שבין פרשה לפרשה velo mipnei revach shebein parsha leparsha
or the space of the you know the white space between one
פרשה parsha and the next. Okay so that's in terms of margins
and spacing. Now what happens about going outside of the column of
the column?
You know in English we have like hyphens if something if you
want something to be double-spaced and we space out the letters a
little bit more and we have nice computers that figure out how
to make something be right and left justified. But what happens if
you're doing it as a scribe and you don't have enough space
and we do not do hyphens as you know? So how do
you manage that? נזדמנה לו תיבה בת חמש אותיות nizdamna lo teiva
bat chamesh otiyot so if you happen to come across you're you
know you have a five-letter word to write and you're reaching the
end of the column לא יכתוב שתיים בתוך הדף ושלוש חוץ לדף
lo yichtov shtayim betoch hadaf veshalosh chutz ladaf do not write two
of the letters inside the column and three on the outside. Top
of ל"ב עמוד ב'. lamed bet amud bet. אלא שלוש בתוך הדף
ושתיים חוץ לדף ela shalosh betoch hadaf veshtayim chutz ladaf three within
the column and two can overhang the column. So yes ideally we
want it both right and left justified but if necessary it can
go beyond the column line but not the majority of the word.
The majority of the word you have to figure out how you're
going to get it to be within the actual column itself. נזדמנה
לו תיבה בת שתי אותיות nizdamna lo teiva bat shtei otiyot if
you have a two-letter word לא יזרקנה לבין הדפין lo yizrakena levein
hadapin don't think like oh great I now you told me that
I can do two letters you know outside of the column line
so I'll just do this whole two-letter word בן or something or
יש yesh I'll just do a whole word outside you know in
that column space in that inter-column space. No you cannot do that.
אלא חוזר וכותב בתחילת השיטה. ela chozer vechoteiv bitchilat hashita. Go figure
go write it at the beginning of the next line. Now that's
pretty obvious if you're telling me a five-letter word has to be
the majority on the inside of course you can't have an entire
word on the outside. You should have told me even a three-letter
word can't be one and two. But alright whatever.
הטועה בשם hata'eh bashem now here let's say you make a mistake
in terms of God's name. So apparently what this means you could
imagine different types of mistakes but this is an apparently a mistake
that you did not write God's name where you were supposed to.
It was supposed to be וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר vayedaber Hashem
el moshe leimor and you did וידבר אל משה לאמר. vayedaber el
moshe leimor. So now what do you do? You got the ה'
Hashem that you got to fit in. גורר מה שכתב gorer ma
shekatav
so scrape away and the word גורר gorer is to scrape away
after the ink has dried. Okay so scrape away what has
dried את משה לאמר et moshe leimor scrape that
away ותולה
את מה שגרר. vetoleh et ma shegarar. Okay now let's say you
know you can't like start erasing everything. You've written ten lines since
then. So what are you going to do? So okay וידבר vayedaber
scrape away the אל משה el moshe write the ה' Hashem on
the line itself and then put the אל משה el moshe in
the space between the lines. Remember we told you the lines were
double-spaced?
So put the אל משה el moshe in the space between the
lines in a way that it indicates that those go down next
you know what we would do is we would put a little
caret to show that it means to be inserted. So on the
line itself would be now וידבר ה'. vayedaber Hashem. The ה' Hashem
is written where it used to say אל משה. el moshe. Then
in the space between the two lines it would be אל משה
el moshe which clearly in a way that indicates clearly that they
come next and then back to the line itself לאמר. leimor. Okay
אל
משה. el moshe. So now it
says אלא חוזר וכותב בתחילת ה... ela chozer vechoteiv bitchilat ha... wait
wait הטועה בשם גורר מה שכתב ותולה את מה שגרר וכותב את
השם על מקום הגרר hata'eh bashem gorer ma shekatav vetoleh et ma
shegarar vechoteiv et hashem al mekom hagarar and you write God's name
on the place that you erase. So do you write the name
where it used to say אל משה el moshe and you write
the אל משה el moshe on the top you know between the
line. דברי רבי יהודה. That's רבי יהודה says. רבי יוסי אומר אף
תולין את השם. Rabbi Yossi omer af tulin et Hashem.
No you can just write the י-ה-ו-ה Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei on the line. It
says וידבר אל משה לאמר vayedaber el moshe leimor and then you
just put the י-ה-ו-ה Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei between the וידבר אל vayedaber el and
you put it between the two lines. Clearly the first opinion did
not feel that that would be respectful to
שם ה'. shem Hashem. רבי יצחק אומר. Rabbi Yitzchak omer. רבי יצחק
Rabbi Yitzchak says אף מוחק וכותב. af mochek vechoteiv. No you can
even be מוחק וכותב. mochek vechoteiv. How's that different than גורר? gorer?
rest of the line, so fix it as fast as possible, but
maybe the דף will be a little more stained at that point.
Not exactly clear what the big difference is between גורר gorer and
מוחק. mochek. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri Omer, now רבי
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says, כל השם כולו תולים מקצתו אין
תולים. kol hashem kulo tolin miktzaso ein tolin. So he says you
can be תולה toleh the entire name, you know, not part not
part of the name. So yes, you can put the whole י-ה-ו-ה,
Yud Kay Vav Kay, you know, in the space between the lines,
but you can't put like י-ה Yud Kay in the space between
and the ו-ה Vav Kay in the line itself. So it's a
variation of the תולה את השם toleh es hashem position. רבי שמעון
אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר אין כותבין את השם לא במקום הגרר
ולא במקום המחק Rabbi Shimon Elazar Omer mishum Rabbi Meir ein kotsvin
es hashem lo bimkom hagrar velo bimkom hamachak and now רבי שמעון
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Elazar says you do not write the name, not
where you scraped it away, not where you've erased it away, ואין
תולין אותו ve-ein tolin oso and you also don't stick it between
the lines. So great, so what are you supposed to do? So
you can't do anything according to this position. כיצד עושה? keitzad oseh?
What do you do? מסלק את היריעה כולה וגונזה. mesalek es hayeriah
kulah u-gonzah. You have to now replace your entire קלף klaf now
because there is no way you can fix this, right?
איתמר, itmar, and that can also be a problem if there's a
problem in the שם השם Shem Hashem itself for erase doing some
erasing. You're not erasing the אל משה, el Moshe, you'd have to
actually erase שם השם Shem Hashem and that you're not allowed to
erase שם השם. Shem Hashem. Alright. איתמר, itmar, it was taught. רב
חננאל אמר רב הלכה תולין את השם. Rav Chananel amar Rav halacha
tolin es hashem. רב חננאל Rav Chananel in the name of רב
says you write God's name between the lines. רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רב יצחק בר שמואל הלכה מוחק וכותב. Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel halacha mochek vekhotev. No, you erase the
אל משה el Moshe in the example I've been giving and you
write the השם Hashem on the line and you write the אל
משה el Moshe between the lines וכותב. ולימא מר הלכה כמר ומר
הלכה כמר? velimar mar halacha kemar umar halacha kemar? Why do you
say what the פסק psak was? Why don't you just say which
of the earlier אמוראים Amoraim you're פסקנ'ינג paskening like?
משום דאיחלפי, mishum de-ichalfei, because some people reverse who said what, so
they wanted to be very clear which position they were פסקנ'ינג paskening
like and not just reference the אמורא Amora because maybe it would
get confused or was confused which אמורא Amora said what. אמר רבין
בר חיננא אמר עולא אמר רבי חנינא הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי. Amar
Ravin bar Chinana amar Ulla amar Rabbi Chanina halacha k-Rabbi Shimon Shezuri.
We rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, okay. רבי שמעון
שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri is basically a variation of תולין את השם,
tolin es hashem, he just made it clear that you would only
do the full שם השם, Shem Hashem, you wouldn't do half תולים
tolim and half on the line. ולא עוד אלא כל מקום ששנה
רבי שמעון שזורי הלכה כמותו velo od ela kol makom sheshana Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri halacha kimoso and not only that, whenever רבי שמעון שזורי
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri has an opinion, you know, in a משנה, Mishna,
in a ברייתא, we rule like it. Alright. אהיי. ahai. Now on
what הלכה... halacha... so he said two things. We rule like רבי
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and in general the הלכה halacha is
רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. So what is the anchor of
his case, of his statement? In what case did he say the
הלכה halacha is like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri here and
also in general? אהיי אילימא אהא, ahai eileima aha, רבי שמעון שזורי
אומר כל השם כולו תולים מקצתו אין תולים. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer
kol hashem kulo tolin miktzaso ein tolin. If if that original statement
was made responding to our debate where רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri says, you know, only part, the full name you suspend but
not part. והא איתמר עלה אמר רב חננאל אמר רב הלכה תולין
את השם ורבה בר בר חנה אמר רב יצחק בר שמואל הלכה
מוחק וכותב. veha itmar alah amar Rav Chananel amar Rav halacha tolin
es hashem ve-Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel halacha
mochek vekhotev. So we already heard two later אמוראים, Amoraim, you know,
sort of voicing their position as,
you know, in terms of which of the, you know, which of
the positions they held by.
מוחק וכותב. mochek vekhotev.
ואי איתא... ve-ei isa... מוחק וכותב. mochek vekhotev. So they, you know,
was a מחלוקת תנאים, machlokes tanna'im, I think before I said מחלוקת
machlokes I was saying אמוראים, Amoraim, erase that. Anyway, it's a מחלוקת
תנאים machlokes tanna'im and now you have these אמוראים Amoraim saying which
positions they hold like. ואי איתא ve-ei isa and if this statement
of of עולא Ulla was הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי, halacha k-Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri, this statement was said about our case,
ואי איתא הוא נמי לימא? ve-ei isa hu nami leima? So so
let him also say it. Meaning if you're having אמוראים Amoraim say
how we פסקן, pasken, why was עולא's Ulla's statement that we פסקן
pasken like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri
not said together with those אמוראים? Amoraim? Now who knows, you know,
maybe he wasn't having the same discussion with those אמוראים. Amoraim. But
the גמרא gemara says since we have אמוראים Amoraim discussing which of
these תנאי tannaic positions we rule like, okay, when when עולא Ulla
says we rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, he can't
have been saying it about our case because then he would have
been in discussion with these other אמוראים Amoraim that were also discussing
how we rule in our case. Okay. אלא אהא. ela aha. Fine.
So עולא's Ulla's statement that we go like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri was said on the following position of רבי שמעון שזורי.
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר אפילו בן חמש שנים וחורש
בשדה שחיטת אמו מטהרתו. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer afilu ben chamesh shanim
ve-choresh basadeh shechitas imo meta-araso. So this is about a בן פקועה,
ben pakua, you shecht... Slaughtered a cow and inside of it you
found a fully grown, you know, calf that had not yet been
born, that calf is now walking around and healthy and so on,
that calf does not need שחיטה shechita because the שחיטה shechita that
was done to the mother when it was in the mother's womb,
it was just like a piece of the mother, like a leg.
Now it's a piece of mother that has been animated and has
become an entire calf, okay, but the שחיטה shechita of the mother
made it permissible. And רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri said, even
if this calf is five years old and it's been plowing in
your field and everybody thinks it's a normal calf, you can go
ahead and eat it without שחיטה. shechita. And obviously the pushback would
be, that's a little מראית עין maris ayin and that could be
a little bit of, you know, sort of misleading people, but he
says, I don't care, go ahead and eat it without שחיטה. shechita.
So maybe that's where this statement that we go like רבי שמעון
בן שזורי Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri was anchored in? No, הא איתמר
עלה, ha itmar alah, it was said on that, זעירי אמר רבי
חנינא הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי, Zeiri amar Rabbi Chanina halacha k'Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri, that we already have another אמורא Amora who says we rule
like רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. ואי איתא הוא נמי לימא,
v'ei isa hu nami leima, and if עולא's Ulla statement that we
go like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri was anchored in this
position of רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri about the cow, then
he should have said it together with זעירי אמר רבי חנינא, Zeiri
amar Rabbi Chanina, same point. If another אמורא Amora is already discussing
how we rule in that case, then why wasn't עולא Ulla part
of that conversation? And since he wasn't part of that conversation, it
indicates that his statement was not said about that ruling. אלא הא,
Ella ha, fine, let's try this ruling of רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri. בראשונה היו אומרים היוצא בקולר ואמר כתבו גט לאשתי, Berishona
hayu omrim hayotzei bekolar v'amar kisvu get l'ishti, this is a משנה.
Mishna. Originally they said that somebody that was being taken out in
chains and about to be executed and said to witnesses, write a
גט get for my wife, because if he's executed and then he
has a brother and then he doesn't have kids, then his wife
is going to be חייב chayav in יבום yibum with his brother.
So if he wants to save his wife from יבום, yibum, he
wants to get her divorced before she becomes a widow. So he
says, write a גט get to my wife. The only thing is
that he didn't say, write it and deliver it to my wife.
And when it comes to a גט, get, you need to make
a שליח shaliach to both do the writing and a שליח shaliach
to do the delivering. Each one requires שליחות. shlichus. So under normal
circumstances if somebody said to עדים, eidim, write a גט get for
my wife, they would not be empowered to give it. Maybe he
just wants it available if and when he ever wants to use
it. But in this case we interpret what he is saying to
mean הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu, the witnesses can
sign, write it, sign it, and deliver it. We assume that that
is what he meant based on the context, and the reason that
he didn't say it we assume is he was a little distracted.
He was being taken out in chains. Okay, that used to be
the original ruling, limited to a case of a guy being taken
out to be executed. חזרו לומר, Chazru lomar, they went back to
say אף המפרש והיוצא בשיירא, af hamifaresh v'hayotzei bishayara, even somebody that
was going on a caravan or going out for a sea journey,
same thing. He didn't want, maybe he wouldn't return, his wife would
be an עגונה, aguna, maybe even worse than the יבום yibum situation.
So he said, write a גט get for my wife. And we
assume why is he saying this just as he's about to leave?
So obviously he means write it and deliver it. Now, the reason
this is different is because here he's a little bit more in
control, like he's not being taken out to be executed, he's going
on a journey.
Nevertheless, the boat is leaving, the caravan is leaving, you're being rushed,
and based on context we assume you mean not only write it
and sign it but also deliver it. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר, Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri omer, רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says, אף המסוכן,
af hamesukan, even somebody that is like in danger, you know, he's
anything of danger. So again, not like he's leaving and he's rushing
out and so on, maybe somebody that I don't know found out
they have cancer, you know, but the same degree of urgency,
and there's a degree of context, but it's not the same degree
of urgency, so maybe we wouldn't say it means deliver unless he
explicitly says deliver, but רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri is willing
to say that is what he meant. Okay,
so maybe that's the case where עולא Ulla said we rule like
רבי שמעון שזורי? Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? I mean, he says we always
rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, but that's the case
it was anchored in. Okay, so הגמרא Hagemara says, אי נמי הא,
ei nami ha, fine, so maybe that one. אי נמי הא, Ei
nami ha, or maybe it could be the following one.
תרומת מעשר של דמאי שחזרה למקומה. trumas ma'aser shel demai shechazra limkoma.
You took דמאי, demai, דמאי demai is grain that we don't know
that we buy from, you know, normal farmers, עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
people not really part of the rabbinic class, and we have to
be concerned that they did not take מעשרות ma'asros from it. We
assume they took תרומה, truma, but they didn't take מעשר, ma'aser, and
then they didn't take תרומת מעשר, trumas ma'aser, which is a tenth
of the tenth and has a status of תרומה. terumah. Okay, now
let's say the earlier teaching here had been in the משנה mishnah
that if somebody purchased this דמאי demai produce and then it became
שבת, shabbos, okay, and he has not yet taken מעשר ma'aser from
this דמאי, demai, מעשר ma'aser and תרומת מעשר. terumat ma'aser. So since
it's שבת shabbos and he has nothing else to eat, חז"ל chazal
were lenient and they said you could go ahead and ask the
person you bought it from, hey, did you take מעשר? ma'aser? And
if the guy says yes, in this case we'll allow you to
trust him. תוספות tosafot also quotes a ירושלמי yerushalmi I think that
says that partly it's also אימת שבת על עמי הארץ. eimat shabbos
al amei ha'aretz. Because you're asking on שבת shabbos and it's a
very holy day, the עם הארץ am ha-aretz is more likely to
be telling the truth. So they allowed you to ask the עם
הארץ am ha-aretz if it was שבת shabbos and you didn't take
it beforehand, and according to רש"י rashi also because you don't have
other food to eat. All right, so now what happens if though
you did take מעשר ma'aser before שבת shabbos and you took תרומת
מעשר terumat ma'aser which is קודש, kodesh, it's תרומה, terumah, you can't
eat it if you're not a כהן. kohen. And then the תרומה
terumah fell back into the produce and got mixed up. So now
all the fruit is אסור, assur, all the fruit is אסור, assur,
because it has a mixture of תרומה terumah in it. So רבי
שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon shezuri says, so says תרומת מעשר של דמאי
שחזרו למקומה. terumat ma'aser shel demai she-chezru l'mekoma. So that happened, you
took the תרומת מעשר terumat ma'aser and it went back, got mixed,
and now it's שבת. shabbos. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר אף בחול שואלו
ואוכלו על פיו. rabbi shimon shezuri omer af bechol sho'alo v'ochlo al
piv. In this case where you'd have to throw out the entire
mixture, here they allowed you even to ask him on a weekday
and not דוקא davka for שבת shabbos purposes and trust his answer.
So if he says yes, I took תרומה, terumah, I took מעשר
ma'aser already from it, you can say oh, so my whole taking
of מעשר תרומת מעשר ma'aser terumat ma'aser was all unnecessary and didn't
count, and therefore everything is okay. So okay, not just for שבת
shabbos purposes but even during the weekday if it would mean you
would have to otherwise throw out your entire mixture. Okay, so let's
say those one of those cases was the one where עולא's ulla
ruling like רבי שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon shezuri is anchored. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואיתמר עלה, v'itmar alah, one minute, we taught on
it, אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי במסוכן. amar rabbi yochanan
halacha k'rabbi shimon shezuri be-mesukan. רבי יוחנן rabbi yochanan said we rule
like רבי שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon shezuri in the case of the
מסוכן, mesukan, the guy going out, you know, the guy who's in
danger says write a גט get for my wife, ובתרומת מעשר של
דמאי u-v'terumat ma'aser shel demai in this case of the תרומת מעשר
terumat ma'aser of דמאי. demai. ואי איתא הוא נמי לימא. v'ei isah
hu nami leima. And if עולא's ulla statement was referring to one
of these cases, then he should have been in conversation with רבי
יוחנן. rabbi yochanan. Same point again and again and again. You know,
it's very he said we rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, rabbi shimon
shezuri, but he said it as a loner. He didn't say it
in conversation with any other אמורא. amora. So anytime an אמורא amora
ruled like רבי שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon shezuri or ruled about the
case that רבי שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon shezuri had an opinion, we
can't say that's the case that עולא ulla was talking about because
then he would have been in conversation with that אמורא. amora. So
we have to find a case of רבי שמעון שזורי rabbi shimon
shezuri where no אמורא פסק amora pasak about the case, and that
is the anchor case of עולא. ulla. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא הא, ela ha, fine, going on this case. רבי יוסי
בן כיפר אומר משום רבי שמעון שזורי. rabbi yosei ben kipar omer
mishum rabbi shimon shezuri. רבי יוסי בן כיפר rabbi yosei ben kipar
says in the name of רבי שמעון שזורי, rabbi shimon shezuri, פול
המצרי, pul ha-mitzri, this Egyptian legume שזרעו לזרע she-zaro le-zera that you
planted it for the seeds. If you plant it, you know, for
the leafy part of it, then the תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot goes
from when it's picked. But if you plant it for the seeds,
you know, then it goes when it takes root. So you planted
it because you wanted to eat the seeds. מקצתו השריש לפני ראש
השנה ומקצתו השריש לאחר ראש השנה. miktzato hishrish lifnei rosh hashanah u-miktzato
hishrish achar rosh hashanah. Some of it took root before ראש השנה
rosh hashanah and some after. So some of this plant is obligated
in תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u-ma'asrot, let's say from year two, and others
תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot from year three. And the problem is they're
different מעשר ma'aser year two and year three. And also you can't
take from one year to the next. But they're all growing from
the same plant, so what do you do? So אין תורמין מזה
על זה, ein tormin mizeh al zeh, you can't take תרומה terumah
from one to the other לפי שאין תורמין ומעשרין לא מן החדש
על הישן ולא מן הישן על החדש. lefi she-ein tormin u-ma'asrin lo
min hachadash al hayashan v'lo min hayashan al hachadash. Or maybe they're
two different plants but they're all mixed up in the same, you
know, row. So you have a thousand of these plants and some
of them from before ראש השנה, rosh hashanah, some after, who knows
which is which, right? What are you supposed to do? You can't
take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot from old to new.
So כיצד יעשה, keitzad ya'aseh, what do you do? צוברו גורנו לתוכו.
tzovro gorno le-tocho. So you basically, you know, harvest them all into
the same threshing floor, into the same, you know, location. ונמצא, v'nimtza,
and then you take the תרומה, terumah, you know, you take ten
percent, you know, ten percent מעשר, ma'aser, you take whatever your percent
of תרומה, terumah, two percent תרומה, terumah, and you basically assume that
it all mixed equally, has mixed equally. So if it is, you
know, let's say it's I don't know sixty from the previous year
and forty percent from the current year, and you take ten percent...
percent of the whole mixture, you're going to assume and you call,
"This is מעשר Maaser on the whole mixture," so then you're going
to assume of that 10 percent, 60 percent of it was the
last year and 40 percent of that 10 percent was the current
year and each one is working for its appropriate year.
So perhaps this is the case where עולא Ulla in the name
of רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said that we פוסקן Pasken like רבי
שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, maybe this is the anchor case, and
but the גמרא says no, we got another problem with this, once
again it is something that already there has been a discussion of
the אמוראים Amoraim and עולא Ulla then should have had his statement
as part of that discussion. So the גמרא says איתמר עלה, haitmar
ala, but it was said on that, אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan, said
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה רבי שמעון שזורי,
halacha Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, we rule
like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri in that case, ואם איתא,
veim ita, and if it was that
עולא Ulla רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina statement was referring to that case
when it said הלכה רבי שמעון שזורי, halacha Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, הוא
נמי לימא, hu nami leima, he should also have been part of
that discussion with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And since he said it
independent of any discussion with אמוראים, Amoraim, he could not have been
referring to this case. Okay, we will stop there for today.